<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hoary head crowned a sermon preached at Brackley at the funerall of Fran. Walbank, a very aged and religious matron / by Thomas Hodges ...</title>
            <author>Hodges, Thomas, d. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14545</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12851298</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12851298</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44071)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 383:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hoary head crowned a sermon preached at Brackley at the funerall of Fran. Walbank, a very aged and religious matron / by Thomas Hodges ...</title>
                  <author>Hodges, Thomas, d. 1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leon. Lichfield ... for Tho. Robinson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walbank, Frances, d. 1652?</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XLI, 31 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94527:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> HOARY HEAD CROWNED.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at BRACKLEY at the <hi>Funerall of</hi> FRAN: WALBANK, A Very Aged and Religious MATRON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY Thomas Hodges</hi> B. D. Rector of <hi>Souldern,</hi> and lately one of the Sen: Fellows of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Johns Coll. Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by LEON. LICHFIELD Printer to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> for THO. ROBINSON. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:94527:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94527:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO HIS</hi> VERY AGED AND MUCH HONOVRED Grand-father JOHN MORLEY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD having multiplied your dayes to Foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeares and upwards, and your Seed to above an hundred, and in both reſpects ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored you; Give me leave I pray you, (who under God, had my being from you at first, and many bleſſings ſince) according to my bounden duty; to Endeavour (ſo far as I am able) to honour You before the people. The truth is this Text I deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have preached upon to your ears; but that purpoſe miſcarrying, I am bold to preſent it here into your hands. And becauſe, through distance of place and other Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I cannot hope to Preach often to you, or ſpeak with you face to face; I ſhall not content my ſelfe with the bare tender of one ſingle Sermon to your eyes; But ſhall take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, with your favour, to direct you how to Preach to your ſelfe dayly, when other preachers are abſent, or ſilent, or cannot through your age be heard; And how to Commune with your own heart, and ſpeak to your ſelf, when you have none elſe with whom you may converſe, or when your ſelf may be ſpeechleſſe. To this purpoſe, that the Preacher in your boſome (your own conſcience) may never want a ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Text, and matter for a ſoul-ſaving Sermon, let me Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94527:3"/> to your moſt ſerious ſtudy and dayly meditation eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially three Scripture-Dialogues, or Conferences, &amp; two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes. The Conferences are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That which you read in the 2. of <hi>Samuel: 19:34, 35, 36.</hi> which was betwixt King <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Barzillai;</hi> wherein you may ſee the vanity of all earthly delights, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in old age.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>Nicodemus</hi> a maſter in <hi>Iſrael Iohn: 3.4, 5, 6, 7.</hi> verſ: Wherein is taught the neceſſity of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all, old and young, before they can enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven; and where is made good that other ſaying, which is written <hi>2. Corinth: 5.17. If any man</hi> (whether young or old) <hi>be in Chriſt he is a new creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That betwixt our Saviour and <hi>Martha</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her brother <hi>Lazarus: Iohn 11:21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27.</hi> where we find, that <hi>beleeving in the Lord Ieſus</hi> (which in <hi>Ioh: 7:37, 38.</hi> is expounded to be a <hi>coming unto him</hi>) is the only way to attain to life in and after death, even to attain to the reſurrection of the dead.</p>
            <p>The Promiſes are Firſt, that which is recorded <hi>Eſaiah: 46:4, 5.</hi> which although it be propounded to the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> in generall, yet it truly and particularly belongs to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that is an Iſraelite indeed: <hi>Hearken unto me, O houſe of Iacob, and all the remnant of the houſe of Iſrael, which are born by me from the belly, which are carried from the womb, and even to your old age I am he, and even to hoarie haires will I carry you: I have made, and I will bear, even I will carrie, and I will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other is written Hoſ: <hi>13.14. I will ranſome them from the power of the grave: I will redeem them from death: O death I will be thy plagues: O grave I will be thy deſtruction.</hi> I know 'tis true, <hi>that it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to men once to dye,</hi> Heb. 9.27. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94527:3"/> this promiſe. Yet the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us that at last, <hi>This corruptible muſt put on incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and this mortall muſt put on immortality,</hi> and that the time will come <hi>whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal be brought to paſſe, the ſaying that is written, death is ſwallowed up in victory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.53, 54.</note> Theſe two promiſes, laid hold on by faith, may ſerve as <hi>two ſtaves,</hi> and both of them <hi>ſtaves of beauty,</hi> wherewith to ſupport your old age, and to ſtay you when you walk through the valley of the ſhaddow of death, and near the mouth of the pit, that you fall not. I ſhall no further preach to you, but leave the application to the Preacher within you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned. Yet I ſhall not let you goe till I pray for you, and bleſſe you. 'Tis more uſuall for Parents to lay up prayers and bleſſings for their Children, then Children for their Parents: Yet I remember that <hi>Melchizedech,</hi> the Preiſt of the High-God, bleſſed <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull: And conſider that it is one part of the Preiſts of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to bleſſe the people; And therefore I hope, that (being a preacher deſcended from your own loynes, and having in this Epiſtle and Sermon thus taken upon me to preach to you) I ſhall not be offenſive, if herein I come unto you too, as a miniſter, in the fulneſſe of the bleſſings of the Goſpel of Chriſt, if I bleſſe you alſo, O my father. The Lord convince you more and more of the need of a Saviour, of the worth of Jeſus: The Lord help you to roll your ſelf living and dying upon the mercies of God &amp; the merits of Chriſt: You have a double Crown already, that of a hoary head, and that of a Grand-father, (for <hi>Childrens Children are the Crown of old men: Prov: 17:6.</hi> But both theſe are Corruptible: Oh that you may have <hi>a Crown of righteouſneſſe,</hi> that <hi>Crown of Glory which fadeth not away, reſerved in heaven for you:</hi> May your Gray haires never come with ſorrow to the grave: but that after God hath added to your dayes (if it be his will) many more years, your good old
<pb facs="tcp:94527:4"/> age (in which, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, we ſhall ſay, we have no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) may be ſwallowed up in a happy and bleſſed Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: And that you may for ever there in joy God our and your firſt and laſt father, and live with him; <hi>In whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is fulneſſe, of Ioy, and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So prayeth, Your moſt Dutifull and Affectionate Sonne</hi> Thomas Hodges.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Novemb. <hi>23: 1652.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94527:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 16.31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Hoary Head is a crowne of Glory, if it be found in the way of Righteouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Text is the old mans Patent of Honour. The <hi>hoary head,</hi> that is <hi>old age,</hi> or the <hi>old man,</hi> is a <hi>crowne of glory,</hi> that is, is <hi>honourable</hi> and <hi>glorious,</hi> is to be <hi>reverenced</hi> and <hi>honoured</hi> by us: As we reverence thoſe upon whoſe heads men ſet crownes and Diadems of ſilver and gold; ſo eſpecially ought we to honour thoſe men, whom the God of heaven (the firſt fountaine of all Honour) doth crown with a <hi>Hoary head,</hi> or <hi>white haires,</hi> by reaſon of age. The latter part of the verſe is <hi>diverſly</hi> tranſlated; ſome have it thus, <hi>it is found,</hi> or <hi>ſhall be found</hi> in the way of righteouſneſſe: and then the ſenſe is this, <hi>honorable old age is to be attained in the way of righteouſneſſe,</hi> or to live well is the way to <hi>live long.</hi> Our laſt tranſlators have put in the word <hi>if</hi> which is not in the Originall, to note that then old men are moſt to be honoured when they are religious, when they walk in the way of righteouſneſſe. according as the <hi>Geneva</hi> tranſlation hath it. <hi>Age is a Crowne of glory when it is found in the way of righteouſneſſe.</hi> Both theſe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations hold forth a truth, <hi>viz:</hi> that God doth give long
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94527:5"/> life <hi>to godly</hi> &amp; <hi>Religious men:</hi> &amp; that <hi>we ought to give more eſpeciall honour to holy and religious old men.</hi> Thoſe men, who beſides the ſilver crown of old age, have upon their heads the golden crown of religion, are moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by God, and ought ſo to be by men. The ſumme of all may amount to thus much. <hi>viz. That a good old age which God uſually, or ordinarily, bestowes upon good men, is honourable, and glorious; or ought to render them very honourable in our eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall take occaſion from this Text to treat of the honour of old age, and to that purpoſe I ſhall endevour to ſhew,
<list>
                  <item>1. That old age is honourable and glorious.</item>
                  <item>2. Why old age is ſo honourable.</item>
                  <item>3. How we are to honour old age.</item>
                  <item>4. By what meanes we may attain to the honour of old age.</item>
                  <item>5. What is that old age upon which God and good men, beſtow the moſt abundant honour.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the firſt. Old age <hi>is truly honourable,</hi> Whether we conſult the law of Scripture, or the law of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; either <hi>God's</hi> or <hi>man's</hi> Heraldrie.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God hath commanded us to honour the hoarie head; thus ſhall it be done to the man whom the King of heaven delighteth to honour. <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.32. <hi>Thou ſhalt riſe up before the hoarie head, and honour the face of the old man, and fear thy God;</hi> as ever thou feareſt the Lord thy God, ſee that thou reverence age; yea 'tis <hi>the firſt commandement with promiſe. Eph:</hi> 6:7. That which requires us to honour old age under the name of father and mother, tis the firſt commandement which hath any <hi>ſpeciall</hi> promiſe annexed unto it; <hi>old men</hi> are comprehended within this commandement as <hi>fathers,</hi> and <hi>old women,</hi> as <hi>mothers.</hi> 1. <hi>Timoth:</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94527:5"/> not an elder, but intreat him as a father and the younger men as brethren: the elder women as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers &amp;c.</hi> And, becauſe the mother is uſually moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, therefore 'tis thought that in <hi>Levit:</hi> 19:3. God commands the fear of the mother, in the firſt place, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Ye ſhall fear every man his Mother and his Father.</hi> Again, becauſe the devill will teach us to break over the hedg where 'tis loweſt, namely to ſlight our mother in her old age, becauſe of the weakneſſe of her ſex, and of the infirmites of old age concurring together: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath God not left himſelfe without witneſſe, nor us without warning againſt this ſin; But hath made eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all proviſion to ſtop this gap and to make up, and make ſtrong this fence, with that ſaying <hi>Proverbs</hi> 23:22. <hi>Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto thy father that begat thee and deſpiſe not thy mother when ſhee is old:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Scripture makes <hi>this</hi> an argument of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of all politie and good government in a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or State, when the aged are not duely honoured. So much is intimated: <hi>Eſa:</hi> 3:5. <hi>the child ſhall behave him felfe proudly againſt the ancient, and the baſe againſt the honourable.</hi> And indeed when once it comes to this, that every boy, or young ſtripling, dares demean himſelf inſolently towards the ancient, whom he ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence &amp; honour; then behold confuſion in every ſtate according as is threatned <hi>Eſa.</hi> 24:2, 3. Then farewell all good order and diſtinction and regard of perſons in Church and State, It was a ſad preſage of the mine of the Jewes, that <hi>they reſpected not the perſons of the Priests, and that they favoured not,</hi> or accepted not, <hi>the elders,</hi> or ancients. <hi>Lament:</hi> 4:16: If we underſtand the place of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> as ſome: Or elſe it is accounted <hi>barbarouſneſſe</hi> even in an enemy, not to reſpect calling, or <hi>age,</hi> not to reſpect the <hi>Priests,</hi> not to favour the <hi>Elders,</hi> if we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94527:6"/> the place of the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> as others. Agreeable hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we read in 2: <hi>Chron:</hi> 37:17: <hi>that the King of the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees had no compaſſion on young man or maiden, old man or him that stooped for age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We find in 1: <hi>Sam:</hi> 2:30: that when God threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Eli's</hi> houſe to degrade them from their honour; he preſently addeth <hi>v:</hi> 31, 32, 33: (once and again) <hi>there ſhall not be an old man in thy houſe: and a</hi> third time: <hi>all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of thine houſe ſhall dye in the flower of their age:</hi> But on the contrary, to dye in a <hi>good old age,</hi> is ſpoken of as a <hi>bleſſing, Job</hi> 5:26: <hi>thou ſhalt come to thy grave in a full age, like as a ſhock of corne commeth in in his ſeaſon:</hi> that is, as the corn ſtands againſt all <hi>stormes</hi> of wind and rain untill it be <hi>fully ripe,</hi> and then is gathered into barn, (being firſt made up in ſhocks,) ſo ſhalt thou ſtand upon the earth, and not be <hi>ruined,</hi> or <hi>reaped</hi> whilſt thou art green, till thou art <hi>ripe</hi> and <hi>full of dayes;</hi> and then, and not till then, ſhalt thou come to thy grave as <hi>ripe corne</hi> into barne. Yea 'tis promiſed to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> after the returne from the Captivity, <hi>Zachar:</hi> 8:4: that there ſhould <hi>yet old men and old women dwell in her streets, and every man with his staff in his hand for verie age.</hi> Let me add that <hi>Romans</hi> 9:4. 'tis reckoned amongſt the honourable priviledges of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (as that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> was their brother according to the fleſh, ſo) that <hi>theirs</hi> were the <hi>Fathers.</hi> And thus much may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the Blazoning of this ancient Coat of Honour according to Scripture Heraldrie.</p>
            <p>I might alſo ſhew, how the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who had only the light of <hi>nature,</hi> yet did reverence and honour old age. <hi>Plato</hi> in his Common-wealth, ordered, that the <hi>Elders</hi> ſhould be honoured. <hi>Ovid</hi> tels us how of old time they were reverenced amongſt the <hi>Romanes. Lib:</hi> 5. <hi>Faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Magna fuit quondam capitis reverentia cani,</l>
               <l>Inque ſuo precio ruga ſenilis erat.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94527:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Juvenal</hi> ſaith, that in the golden age, they counted it a <hi>capital</hi> crime if a young man, (though a rich man, did not riſe up to an old man, though a poore man,) <hi>Juve: Sat.</hi> 13.
<q>
                  <l>Credebant hoc grande nefas &amp; morte piandum,</l>
                  <l>Si Juvenis vetulo non aſſurexerit. &amp;c.</l>
               </q> And this may ſuffice to have been ſpoken for the proof of the firſt thing propounded, namely, that old age is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and glorious</p>
            <p n="2">II. Of the ſecond. <hi>viz: Why old men are ſo honourable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe they are an honour to the place where they live: <hi>living monuments of Honour.</hi> They honour <hi>us,</hi> and therefore 'tis but reaſon we ſhould honour <hi>them.</hi> Antiquity is very attractive; that ſide old men goe on uſually bears the greateſt ſway and authority: Old men are loadſtons to draw younger ones their way. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there was not ſo great a conteſt about the young child before <hi>Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe it was;</hi> as there is to this day betwixt us Proteſtants and the Papiſts, about the <hi>ancient fathers</hi> of the Primitive Church: The Romaniſts ſay, the <hi>fathers</hi> are theirs; and We ſay; <hi>Nay,</hi> but the <hi>fathers</hi> are <hi>ours:</hi> nor without marvell for <hi>non ſum melior patribus</hi> (I am not better then the fathers,) is a Motto well becomming the beſt man, and greateſt Scholar.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they are an help to the ſocieties, whereof they are members, in reſpect of their <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> much increaſed by their long <hi>experience</hi> in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affairs. As they are the <hi>Crown</hi> of a people, ſo they are their <hi>councell.</hi> The great court of the Jewes was cal'd the councell of the <hi>ſeventy Elders:</hi> and the great court of Rome the <hi>Senat,</hi> &amp; their Counſellours <hi>Senators</hi> (from <hi>ſenes</hi> old men,) and Fathers, <hi>Patres conſcripti;</hi> and in the New Teſtament, the Church conſiſtorie is cal'd the <hi>Elderſhip;</hi> and the <hi>Church-officers, Presbyters or Elders.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94527:7"/> From all which, we may gather, that the Judgment of <hi>old men,</hi> is uſually better then of <hi>younger</hi> men: according to that <hi>Job Ch:</hi> 12:12. <hi>with the ancient is wiſdome</hi> and in <hi>length of days is understanding.</hi> This is likewiſe intimated <hi>Levit:</hi> 11:32. where inſtead <hi>of thou ſhalt riſe up before the hoarie head: the Chaldee Paraphraſe hath it, thou ſhalt riſe up before the wiſe. And Eſa:</hi> 3.2. God threatens to take away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Judah &amp; Jeruſalem, as <hi>the mighty man and the man of warr, ſo the prudent and the Ancient:</hi> The prudent and ancient are equivalent termes. 'Tis very remarkable that when <hi>Rehoboam</hi> forſook the advice of the old Counſellers, he ſoon loſt ten tribes at a clap.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe old men are, in a ſort, <hi>God's deputies</hi> and <hi>vice-roys</hi> here in the world. They ſeem nearer to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the ancient of daies, then the young generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doe. I know indeed that, properly and ſtrictly, God is not old: for <hi>vetus Deus aliquando non erit:</hi> as <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus Deus aliquando non fuit:</hi> for that which waxeth old, ſaith the Scripture, is neer unto vaniſhing away, yet he is ſtil'd in Scripture the <hi>Ancient of daies;</hi> the <hi>Everlasting Father;</hi> the <hi>God of Eternity.</hi> And it is an argument, that the religion of the Gentiles was not the moſt ancient, becauſe their Gods were but younglings: their genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy and pedegree was known. It was objected by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius</hi> to the heathen, that not onely <hi>recens nata erat e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum religio, ſed et dii ipſi erant infantes &amp; parvuli</hi> and ſuch as had need of milk, and not of <hi>strong meat,</hi> ſuch as were their ſacrifices of ſheep, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Of the third, <hi>How we are to honour old men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt <hi>riſe up before the hoarie head. Levit.</hi> 19:32. God proclaimes before them, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> cauſed to be proclaimed before <hi>Joſeph, Abrech i.e. Bow the knee:</hi> Or not much unlike to that which was proclaimed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mordecai, by the commandement of <hi>Ahaſueroſh;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94527:7"/> Loe thus ſhal it be done to the good old man, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the King of heaven delights to honour.</hi> God who is himſelfe no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepter of Perſons, or faces, yet commands us to reſpect the Perſon, or face of the <hi>old man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 We muſt <hi>ſpeak honourably of them, and reverently to them.</hi> 1 <hi>Timoth:</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>rebuke not an elder, but entreat him as a father. &amp;c.</hi> In the 2 of <hi>Kings:</hi> 13.14. We find even wicked King <hi>Joaſh,</hi> King of Iſrael, coming to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the old Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> when he was ſick; weeping o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his face, <hi>Oh my father, my father; the Charets of Iſrael and the horſmen thereof:</hi> bewailing <hi>Eliſha,</hi> with the ſame words, wherewith he had, above 50 years before be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed his maſter <hi>Elija: Ch:</hi> 2: <hi>v.</hi> 12. of the ſame Book.</p>
            <p n="3">3: Give old men the honour of <hi>ſpeaking firſt,</hi> and the honour of due <hi>attention. Job</hi> 32.7: <hi>I ſaid, dayes ſhould ſpeak, and multitude of years ſhould teach wiſdome.</hi> Let old men in <hi>Civills</hi> be your Oracles: the Poets fain young <hi>Phaeton,</hi> to have ſet the world on fire: You will find it, for the moſt part, no <hi>fiction,</hi> that young men are the <hi>hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurs the Incendiaries,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſet Church &amp; ſtate on a flame:</p>
            <p n="4">IV Of the fourth, <hi>How we may attain to the honour of old age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I anſwer,</hi> We may find it in the way of <hi>righteouſneſse; Seek the kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe.</hi> Get part in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt; and, as he is righteous ſo <hi>be ye righteous in all manner of Converſation;</hi> &amp; this is indeed <hi>Via recta ad vitam longam,</hi> the right way to long life, yea to <hi>everlasting life;</hi> for <hi>godlineſſe hath the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this life, and of that which is to come.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4:8. And again, <hi>the fear of the Lord prolongeth dayes,</hi> but the <hi>years of the wicked ſhall be ſhortned, Prov:</hi> 10:27. add to this, that of the Pſalmiſt <hi>Pſ:</hi> 55:23. <hi>the bloody and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man ſhall not live out half his dayes:</hi> His <hi>Sun</hi> ſhall goe <hi>down</hi> before 'tis noon: But more particularly: I Get
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94527:8"/> 
               <hi>ſpirituall ſaving wiſdome,</hi> that is, get Chriſt, and he will give thee long life, <hi>Prov:</hi> 16:3. and 4.20, 21, 22. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of the <hi>father,</hi> he hath life, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow, and to whomſoever he will he giveth it. <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) that is, I am the true way unto life. With Chriſt is the well-ſpring, the fountain <hi>of life, of naturall, ſpirituall, and eternall</hi> life: Aſk of him, and he will give thee <hi>living water.</hi> He hath <hi>living water</hi> and <hi>living bread,</hi> and a <hi>tree</hi> of <hi>life</hi> to give thee: and he that eats or drinks of theſe, ſhall live for ever. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>This poor man cryed, and the Lord heard him;</hi> and for what did he aſk, and did God hear him? He aſked life of him, and he gave him <hi>life,</hi> even <hi>length of daies</hi> for ever and ever. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 21:4: <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Long life is to be attained by our <hi>honouring</hi> of &amp; <hi>obedience</hi> to our parents and <hi>elders. Exod:</hi> 20. <hi>Honour thy father &amp; thy mother, that they may lengthen thy dayes:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>prolongabunt dies tuos.</hi> Obedient children are children of many prayers, and the parents prayers, are the meanes under God, whereby is procured to them <hi>long life.</hi> Hence Parents prayers are called bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. Beſides 'tis equal, (ſaith one) that ſuch as honour thoſe by whom they receive life next under God, ſhould have their life continued and prolonged.</p>
            <p n="3">3 If thou deſireſt life and loveſt many dayes, that thou mayeſt ſee good, <hi>keep thy tongue from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and thy lips from ſpeaking guile, Pſ:</hi> 34:12, 13. 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 3, 10. Again, the wiſe man ſpeaks expreſly, <hi>Prov:</hi> 18, 21. <hi>death and life are in the power of the tongue, and he that keepeth his mouth keepeth his life, Prov:</hi> 13.3. Many mens tongues are ſuch ſharp ſwords and razours, as to cut their own throats.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Live</hi> much in <hi>heaven,</hi> if thou wouldeſt <hi>live long
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94527:8"/> upon the earth.</hi> Pſ: 91.14, 15, 16. <hi>Becauſe he hath ſet his love upon me, therefore will I deliver him; I will ſet him on high becauſe he hath known my name: He ſhall call upon me and I will anſwer him, I will be with him in trouble, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him, and honour him: with long life will I ſatiſfy him and ſhew him my ſalvation.</hi> When God ſees men <hi>earthly</hi> minded, 'tis juſt with him to bring them ſpeedily to the <hi>earth,</hi> to ſay unto <hi>them Earth Earth Earth</hi> hear the word of the Lord: <hi>Earth</hi> thou art and unto <hi>Earth</hi> ſhalt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; I ſee thou art an <hi>Earthworm,</hi> and to the <hi>wormes of the Earth</hi> ſhalt thou goe: Thy fleſh ſhall be for meat unto the wormes of the Earth. Oh get more and more, nearer &amp; nearer acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, with God; who is our life and the length of our <hi>dayes:</hi> In his <hi>favour</hi> is <hi>life;</hi> the ſenſe &amp; aſſurance of his love is a <hi>Cordiall wil renew our strength and renew our youth, like the Eagles. Moſes</hi> who talked with God as a man with his friend, Oh how vigorous freſh and lively was he how green and flouriſhing was he to, and in, old age. <hi>Deut:</hi> 34.7. <hi>'tis ſaid his eye was not dim, nor his natural force abated: Enoch</hi> walked with God, and <hi>was tranſlated and ſaw no Corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beloved diſciple John, who lay moſt in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of Chriſt, and had afterwards the greateſt revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the mind of Chriſt concerning his Church; He it was who ſurvived all the reſt of the Apoſtles upon earth. <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe, who whilſt he lived upon earth was rapt up into the third heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, He was ſuch an one as <hi>Paul the aged</hi> (ſo he ſtyles himſelfe) before he dyed: he had the <hi>Crown of old age</hi> before the <hi>Crown of Martyrdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you'l ſay, many times the beſt and towardlieſt children, &amp; moſt righteous young me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dye ſooneſt, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attain to old age: are cropt either in the bud or bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, or whilſt they are green &amp; flouriſhing, whilſt their breaſts are full of milk, and their bones of marrow. We
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94527:9"/> uſually ſay, of thoſe who are remarkably forward in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and goodneſſe above their fellows, they are not like to live long, they are too good for this world. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>whom God loves beſt he takes firſt.</hi> How is it then, you teach us, that Religion and righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, and heavenly-mindedneſſe, are the way to attain to a good old age? eſpecially, when 'tis ſomtimes notoriouſly known that wicked men have the largeſt portion, as of the things of this life, ſo of life it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As concerning religious children which dye ſoon: I anſwer, It may be their Parents doate too much upon them; It may be, they Idolize them: As the wicked Iſraelites ſometimes offered their children unto Idols, unto devils; So too often 'tis ſeen, that good Parents are too too apt to make little gods, that is indeed Idols of their children. And hence God is provoked to take from ſuch Parents the deſire and delight of their eyes, and the dearly beloved of their ſoules. Parents, you may kill your children with overmuch kindneſſe: You may kill the child with <hi>overloving it,</hi> as the Nurſe doth ſometimes with <hi>overlaying it.</hi> If you lay or hang too great a weight, or lean too hard, (that is truſt too much) upon one of theſe young and tender branches, you will ſoon break it off the Tree of life. Children are flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; if you carry them too much in your boſome, they will wither and dye. Oh then forſake not the living God; If you would have right to the living child, leaſt God call this ſinne to remembrance, and ſlay your child even the choyceſt of them.</p>
            <p>Or, 2. I ſay it may be, God takes away ſuch child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren from the evill to come; either from <hi>temptations</hi> which they are likely to be expoſed unto, and in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be overcome by; or from the <hi>evill day coming</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94527:9"/> the place where they lived. God ſaies in ſuch caſes, oh my ſonne, or oh my daughter, <hi>enter into thy chamber, ſhut the door, till theſe calamities be overpaſt.</hi> When there's danger abroad, then Parents look out and fetch home their little ones; and ſo doth God.</p>
            <p>Or, 3. I affirme, that theſe children live much in a little time; that theſe children are <hi>young in years</hi> as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> was, 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 34.3. but <hi>old in grace;</hi> that theſe are the children which dye an hundred years old, as 'tis <hi>Eſ:</hi> 65.20. theſe are like nimble Racers, who run as far in an houre as ſome heavy heeld horſes will goe in a day: theſe are apt ſchollers, who having betimes learnt their leſſon, may have leave to goe home the ſooner: their work is ſoon done, and the Lord of heaven and earth call them home to receive their reward.</p>
            <p>Or 4. It may be ſaid, that theſe children's loſſe of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall life is abundantly recompenced with eternall life. God promiſed <hi>long life,</hi> and he gives them <hi>everlasting</hi> life, doth he doe them any wrong? he promiſed them a <hi>penny</hi> in <hi>ſilver,</hi> and payes them a pound in <hi>Gold,</hi> yea a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of gold, and is he not as good, and better then his word? he promiſed ſuch the ſilver crown of old age, that <hi>corruptible</hi> crown, and he gives them the crown of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of everlaſting life, a crown which is <hi>incorruptible,</hi> and fadeth not away.</p>
            <p>As for good men who dye young, thoſe who are the glory of their time, and yet dye in the flower of their age; I ſay, 'tis either becauſe of ſome diſobedience, or unrighteouſneſſe before grace, or after grace received, for w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God pleaſeth thus temporally to correct them; of this latter ſort were the unworthy Communicants at Corinth. 1. Cor. 11. to whom the bread of <hi>life</hi> became, through their default, the bread of death. Or becauſe men do at too much upon theſe men, and begin to give
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94527:10"/> the glory of God unto theſe, upon whom they ſee his image and ſuperſcription. Or, where 'tis otherwiſe, the caſes and examples are very rare; a few exceptions from the generall rule; and ſuch as have, although a ſhort life, yet a ſweet; ſuch as have the life of life, that is, the comforts and bleſſings of life in abundance, whilſt they live, ſuch as have enough of the things of this life, and of life it ſelfe as much as is good for them, and of the favour of God very much, which is better then life it ſelf: and when they dye, they are paid with uſurie in heaven for the loſſe of a temporary life here. Of whom I may ſay, in a ſenſe, as it was ſaid of <hi>Enoch,</hi> they <hi>are not,</hi> becauſe <hi>God hath taken them;</hi> they walked with God, &amp; they are tranſlated to him.</p>
            <p>As for wicked men, who ſometimes attain to a long life, it may be ſaid that they <hi>are</hi> a great while, rather then that they <hi>live</hi> a great while, as it was ſaid of one, <hi>diu fuit, non diu vixit:</hi> and, as we ſay of a ſhip, which hath been a long time toſſed too and fro by ſtormes and tempeſts, but hath not all that while tended towards the harbour, that ſhe hath been thus long <hi>driven to and fro,</hi> but hath not thus long <hi>ſailed:</hi> So we may ſay of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, they have been a great while toſſed to and fro in the ſea of this world, but they have not ſailed long, becauſe they have come never the nearer to the haven of reſt, after all their toile and labour. Whilſt wicked men live they are farr from God, in whoſe preſence is life, from whoſe favour is the comfort and crown of life, they have bitterneſſe in their greateſt ſweets, and death in their life. The longeſt life of the wicked is but a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, compared to eternity; the ſinner of an hundred years old <hi>lives</hi> not ſo long, but he may be truly and properly ſaid to <hi>dye</hi> eternally.</p>
            <p>To diſmiſſe the objection briefly, know that this is a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94527:10"/> generall rule of Gods own making, that godlineſſe hath the promiſe of this life, and of that which is to come. With long life will God reward and ſatisfie the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man; and at laſt ſhew him his ſalvation in heaven in the life everlaſting. When it falls out otherwiſe, as to temporalls, 'tis either <hi>rare,</hi> and that loſſe abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>repayed</hi> in eternall life; or elſe 'tis a <hi>Chastiſement</hi> for ſome irregular and exorbitant demeanour of our ſelves, or others in relation to us. 'Tis true as the Preacher ſaith, that <hi>all things fall alike to all;</hi> that is, frequently 'tis ſo, and that ſometimes 'tis worſt in outward &amp; worldly reſpects with the beſt of men, <hi>of whom the world is not worthy;</hi> Yet when it is ſo, the fault is in good men themſelves, God is as it were conſtrained, for the love he beares their precious ſoules, to make exceptions from his generall rule, which is <hi>doe well</hi> and <hi>have well</hi> both here and hereafter. <hi>Say ye to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, It ſhall be well with him:</hi> and here the <hi>hoary head</hi> is a <hi>crown of glory,</hi> and it is <hi>found in the way of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. And thus are we come to our fifth head, to ſhew, <hi>what is that old age which is most honourable.</hi> Although all old men (as old men) are in that reſpect honourable, yet they are not all <hi>Peeres</hi> of the Kingdome of heaven. Some Tranſlations render the Text, <hi>When 'tis found in the way of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely the Elders that live <hi>well</hi> are worthy of <hi>double honour;</hi> honour theſe Elders for they are honourable indeed. 'Tis recorded <hi>Act:</hi> 21.16. to the honour of <hi>Mnaſon,</hi> that he was <hi>an old Diſciple. Seniority</hi> in the ſociety of Saints, as Saints, ſhould have honour. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> makes honourable mention of the Elder Converts, <hi>Rom:</hi> 16.7. <hi>Salute Andronicus, and Junia my kinſmen, and my fellow Priſoners, who are of note among the Apostles, who alſo were in Chriſt before me.</hi> But on
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94527:11"/> the other ſide, the <hi>ſinner of an hundred yeares old is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, Eſa:</hi> 65.20. Or as the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> ſaith, <hi>Though a ſinner doe evill an hundred times, and his dayes be prolong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: yet ſurely I know, that it ſhall be well with them that feare God, which feare before him: But it ſhall not be well with the wicked, neither ſhall he prolong his daies which are as a ſhadow, becauſe he feareth not before God, Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtes</hi> 8.12.13. Sinners may ſay, though never ſo hoary headed, <hi>the crown is fallen from our head, woe unto us that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you aſk why <hi>Religious</hi> old <hi>men</hi> are worthy of the greateſt honour: I <hi>anſwer,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe theſe fathers are all, the ſonnes of the moſt high, every one the Son of a King, of the great King of heaven and earth: and they reſemble their heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they who are holy as he is holy. And although Gods children are an aſſembly of firſt borne; yet the <hi>elder</hi> any one is in grace, the <hi>greater</hi> portion of honour ought he to have from, and above his brethren. If the elder by naturall generation and birth be to have <hi>dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble honour,</hi> ſurely the elder by regeneration and a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall new birth much more. We find that good <hi>Shem</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſaak</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> though younger ones, got the birth-right-bleſſing and honour, before their elder brethren.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe religious men are the truely wiſe men, and the longer and greater experience any one hath had in religion, he is the more wiſe, and therefore more honourable. We read <hi>Mat:</hi> 2.1. that there were <hi>wiſe men</hi> came to ſeek Jeſus, to worſhip him, truely they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly called wiſe men, who ever ſeek Jeſus, and when they find him, worſhip him. They ſay the <hi>Turkes</hi> account all <hi>fooles, Saints;</hi> and many amongſt us Chriſtians, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all <hi>Saints fooles.</hi> But the holy Scriptures, which alone are able to make us wiſe unto Salvation, teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94527:11"/> Heare the word of the Lord, <hi>Job</hi> 28.28. <hi>And unto man he ſaid, Behold the feare of the Lord that is wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to depart from evill, is understanding.</hi> And if we will beleeve the wiſeſt of men <hi>(Solomon)</hi> the <hi>Godly</hi> man is the <hi>wiſe man,</hi> but the <hi>Sinner</hi> is the <hi>foole;</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by his oppoſing the ſinner, &amp; the wiſeman <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 9.18. <hi>One ſuch wiſe man</hi> may be a means to <hi>deliver a City. Eccl.</hi> 9.16. and upon that accompt ought to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured. Yea 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 20.16. <hi>&amp;c:</hi> 'Tis recorded that a <hi>wiſe woman</hi> ſaved the City <hi>Abel,</hi> that it periſhed not in the Rebellion of <hi>Sheba</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Bichri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe theſe religious old men are moſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, are the greateſt bleſſings, to the <hi>perſons</hi> with whom, and to the places where they live; they are the Walls and Bullworks of a City, they are the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and pillars of a Nation, they are the Shields of the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> But <hi>what is the ſpeciall honour,</hi> which we muſt do <hi>religious</hi> old men?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We muſt reverence them <hi>inwardly,</hi> in our hearts, and <hi>outwardly,</hi> not in <hi>word</hi> and in <hi>tongue</hi> only, but in <hi>deed</hi> and in <hi>truth.</hi> Whileſt theſe precious Sonns of <hi>Sion,</hi> our Fathers, and Elders, goe on in heaven-way before us, Let us ſtand <hi>by</hi> them, and ſtand <hi>for</hi> them, and in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be wanting <hi>to</hi> them: and when any of them goes up to heaven before us, let that be the language of our hearts, which was ſpoken by <hi>Eliſha</hi> at the taking up of <hi>Elijah, my father, my father, the Chariot of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt obey theſe mens Counſailes, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Let's make them, under God, and the Scripture, our Oracles: Let the counſell of the Elders, be our great and ſupream Councell: Let's honour theſe as good <hi>Job</hi> was honoured. <hi>Ch:</hi> 29.21. <hi>&amp;c:</hi> Let's give eare to theſe, let their ſpeech drop upon us, let us waite for them
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:94527:12"/> man better then his mother, (<hi>viz:</hi> his wife) but he muſt <hi>honour</hi> ſtill his mother before his wife. Conſider her grìevous pangs in bringing us forth at firſt, &amp; her great paines in bringing us up: and ſhe that bare with the thouſand infirmities, weakneſſes and follies of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie and childhood; Let her be borne withall for ſome weakneſſes of her ſex, in her old age: according as it is written <hi>Prov:</hi> 22.22. <hi>deſpiſe not thy mother, when ſhe is old.</hi> And now to conclude this Uſe, Oh that the great peace-maker, after that our families have been divided, Father againſt Son, and Son againſt Father, the Daughter againſt the Mother, and the Mother againſt the Daughter, would (according to his promiſe once made to the Jewes, <hi>Mal:</hi> 4.) Convert or turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and of the children to their fathers, left he come and ſmite our land with a curſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Then honour <hi>old men,</hi> eſpecially <hi>religious</hi> old men. It was Idolatrie, to fall down and worſhip the golden I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, that <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had ſet up; but 'tis Religion, to fall down and worſhip, with Civil worſhip or reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, the religious <hi>old man,</hi> whom God hath ſet up. Goe forth, O ye ſons and daughters of Jeruſalem, and behold the <hi>good old man,</hi> with the <hi>Crown</hi> wherewith his heavenly father hath crowned him, in the day of his <hi>hoary head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Is a good old age to be found in the way of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and righteouſneſſe? Oh then let the young genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who deſire to live long, and to ſee good dayes, let them hence be exhorted to pietie and holineſſe. Come ye children, hearken unto me, and I will teach you the way to live to be honoured old men; live well if you would live long, The more you live to God, the longer you'l live in the world. the Papiſts have a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>Nemo ſeneſcit dum interest Miſſae,</hi> that is, that no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94527:12"/> man is never the older for the time he ſpendes in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſſe. Truly the time we ſpend in religion, and religious exerciſes, is time well ſaved, is time redeemed. They that wait on the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength, their youth ſhall be renewed like the Eagles. <hi>Pſ:</hi> 103. But as for evill doers, the Lord ſhall wound the hairie ſcalp, and the hoarie head too, of him that goes on in his wickedneſſe if he live to age. Well therefore doth the wiſe man adviſe, <hi>Eccleſiastes</hi> 7.17. <hi>Be not overmuch wicked, neither be thou fooliſh, why ſhouldest thou dye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy time?</hi> Men naturally deſire to prolong their dayes: To this end, what <hi>dyet</hi> will they not keep? what <hi>exerciſes</hi> will they not uſe? what <hi>Medicines</hi> will not they take? <hi>skin for skin and all that a man hath will he give for his life.</hi> The Princes and Potentates of the earth have their Phyſitians to counſell them alway what courſe to take, that they may live long upon the earth: But behold I ſhew unto you all this day a more exel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way; and that is the way of the text, the way of righteouſneſſe. Get the Crown of <hi>religion,</hi> if you would have that other crown of a <hi>hoarie head.</hi> The ſame way that leads to <hi>Eternall</hi> life, leads to a <hi>long</hi> life.</p>
            <p>More particularly; as ever you would live to a good old age, Beware of thoſe ſpeciall ſins, which ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily cut the thred of mens lives before the time; which either as <hi>thieves</hi> doe <hi>wast,</hi> or as <hi>winds blow out</hi> the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of life before it is burnt half to the ſocket.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As firſt, If thou deſireſt to live to be old, take heed of <hi>Cains</hi> ſin, the ſin of blood-guiltineſſe: he that is guilty of of blood, may Juſtly fear, leaſt every one that meets him ſhould ſlay him. The Hue and Crie, the blood-hound, the Avenger of blood, doth ordinarily overtake ſuch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore old age. Juſtice ſaith, <hi>Give him blood to drink for he is worthy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:94527:13"/>2. The ſin of <hi>uncleaneſſe,</hi> whether naturall, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall. For <hi>Onan's</hi> ſin the Lord ſlew him. God rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down fire from heaven upon the unclean Sodomites and deſtroyed them ſpeedily; the Lord made a ſhort work with them: and <hi>Prov:</hi> 7.22. 'tis ſaid, <hi>He that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes an harlot, goes as an Oxe to the ſlaughter. Shechems</hi> ſin of uncleanneſſe with <hi>Dinah,</hi> coſt him, his father and the Shechemites their lives. So <hi>Amnon's</hi> inceſt with his ſiſter <hi>Tamar</hi> coſt him his life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Diſobedience</hi> to Parents. When <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nehas</hi> hearkned not to the voyce of their father, it was a ſigne and preſage that the Lord would ſlay them. <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom's</hi> rebellion, againſt his father <hi>David,</hi> cauſed his ſun to ſet at noon. When the children of <hi>Bethel</hi> mock'd the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> ſaying, <hi>goe up thou bald head &amp;c,</hi> (that is, why doeſt not thou goe up to heaven after thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) <hi>two ſhee Bears tore</hi> 42 <hi>of them.</hi> 2 <hi>King:</hi> 2.24.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Covetouſneſſe,</hi> eſpecially if dyed in <hi>oppreſſion,</hi> and <hi>injustice.</hi> Immoderate cares, feares, and exceſſive tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyling, the uſuall concomitants of them that will be rich, do <hi>naturally</hi> ſhorten the life of man: but beſides an untimely death ſeems to be the penalty denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this ſinne, according to the Statute Law of the great Lawgiver, <hi>Jerem:</hi> 17.11. <hi>As the Partridge ſitteth on eggs, and hatcheth them not; ſo he that getteth goods, and not by right, ſhall leave them in the mid'st of his dayes, and at his end ſhall be a foole.</hi> As the Partridg gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth eggs together to ſit on, and to hatch, but hatcheth them not, her eggs either proving windy and addle, as they ſay it oft falleth out with thoſe eggs which ſhe hath produced (as ſhe doth frequently) without the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the male, or otherwiſe miſcarrying, (the male many times breaking them that he may have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of his mate.) Or elſe (as ſome others think) the Partridge, or <hi>Heb:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Kore,</hi> having got together the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94527:13"/> eggs of other Fowles; and ſitting on them as her own, untill they be hatched, they then leave her, and keep with, and follow thoſe of their own kind. So Covetous men deſirous to enrich themſelves by oppreſſion, and taking from others that which is not their owne, and ſitting brooding upon the eggs, or baggs, which they have thus gathered together, at laſt theſe their riches take themſelves wings and fly away. <hi>Prov:</hi> 23.5. or <hi>they</hi> are taken from them. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.20.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Is the hoarie head a crown of glory, if it be found, or when it is found, in the way of righteouſneſſe? then hence we learn, that want of religon in an old man is a great abatement of <hi>honour</hi> in his <hi>Coat.</hi> The beſt flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in his garland, the choyceſt pearle of his crown, is wanting, The old ſinner, together with his crown, hath a curſe upon his head; <hi>the ſinner of a hundred years old is accurſed.</hi> As God and man love an old Friend, ſo they hate and abhorre an old Enimie. Old <hi>ſinners</hi> are like old <hi>toads,</hi> and old ſerpents, the fulleſt of poyſon, and therefore moſt abominable. He is an old <hi>Thiefe,</hi> (ſaith the Judge) away with him, <hi>Away</hi> with him, 'tis not fit ſuch an one ſhould live. So ſaith God, he is an old <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, drunkard, unclean</hi> perſon, <hi>ſwearer, &amp;c:</hi> I have borne with him theſe forty, fifty, or ſixty years and upwards, I crowned every one of thoſe years with my goodneſſe, but (ungratefull, unworthy, wretch!) he hath gone on to rebell againſt me, and goes on to this day and will not turne; Now therefore, oh ye evill angels, this night, or this week, or this yeare, ſee ye that yee require his ſoule of him; or els, oh death let not his hoarie head goe down to the grave in peace, (as <hi>David</hi> charged <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> concerning <hi>Joab,</hi> 1 <hi>King:</hi> 2.6.) or, oh thou ſword of the Lord, his hoar head bring thou down to the grave with blood (as <hi>David</hi> charg'd <hi>Solomon</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Shimei.</hi> 1 <hi>King:</hi> 2.9.)</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:94527:14"/>
            <p>Oh conſider this, ye old men, that have forgotten God, dayes without number, even to this day and hour, conſider this your curſed latter end, if you will not turn your feet into the way of righteouſneſſe; leaſt God tear you in peeces, and there be none to deliver you. For know it for a truth, that the wicked and unrighteous, be they old or young, ſhall be turned into hell, and all the people that forget God.</p>
            <p>Againe, Is old age then honourable when found in the way of righteouſneſſe? Then hence young men may learn how farre they may honour their Fathers and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with the honour of imitation, how farre they may follow their ſteps, <hi>viz:</hi> no farther then they walk in the way of righteouſneſſe, then they follow Chriſt. The old Prophet at <hi>Bethel</hi> deceived the young Prophet, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, in the habit of an old man, in <hi>Samuel</hi>'s mantle, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Saul:</hi> the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> deceived <hi>Joſuah,</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with their old mouldy bread, old ſhooes, &amp; old garments. And alas, how many thouſands amongſt us have been ſeduced, even to oppoſe and fight againſt reformation, upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no other account but this, theſe men will change our old cuſtomes, &amp; our old con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, or manner of converſation received by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from our Fathers. And here let me freely ſpeak unto you old men of this generation: God would have had off your bark of unprofitable Ceremonies, and have made you white and ſtraight ſtaves, even ſtaves of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his hand, and this would not be done without put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting you in the flames of a Civill Warr a while.</p>
            <p>And now be wiſe ye old men, and as you love your ſelves ſee that you oppoſe not reformation; if you ſtand in Gods way, now that he comes as a Refiners fire to purify his Churches from all their tin, and all their droſſe, he'l burn up the old oakes of Baſhan, as very bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and thornes.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:94527:14"/>6. And therefore let me, in the next place, entreat all you old men, to ſuffer a word or two of exhortation from this Text. Be hence perſwaded, oh all ye Elders of the congregation, to be righteous, to be holy. Take un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the Crown of Religion, better then a crown of ſtarrs, all you that have the crown of a hoarie head. To perſwade you hereunto, let me commend to you theſe enſuing Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the caſe of a wicked old man is very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and dreadfull; if he dye in his ſinnes, he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive greater damnation: the Furnace of Hell ſhall be ſeven times hotter for theſe, then for young ſinners. Oh theſe bundles of Tares fully ripe, theſe old rotten Fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots of Bryers and Thornes, (ſo wicked men are called) how ſuddainly, how terribly, will they burne? Certainly it ſhall be more tolerable for <hi>Er</hi> and <hi>Onan,</hi> (who were cutt off betimes in their ſinnes) in the day of Judgment then for the ſinners of a hundred yeares old.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The caſe of a wicked old man, although it be very <hi>dangerous,</hi> yet it is <hi>not deſperate:</hi> Some old feſtered ſoares have been healed; ſome old Chronick diſeaſes have been cured; 'tis not impoſſible to bow an old oake, yea to bend the very heart of oake; art can doe that God is a Chirurgeon can heale old ſoares, a Phyſitian can cure old Diſeaſes; he hath an Arme can bow the heart of Oake; he that can of ſtones raiſe Children to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> can if he pleaſe, and when he pleaſe, of old ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> make Children of God. He that raiſed up <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> after he had been dead <hi>foure dayes,</hi> can raiſe up ſinners, who have been dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes, to the life of grace, to the life of faith, after they have been ſpiritually dead <hi>foureſcore years. The houre cometh and now is,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Joh:</hi> 5.25. <hi>When the dead ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of God, and they that heare ſhall live.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:94527:15"/> Note, 'tis ſaid, <hi>the dead</hi> without any <hi>limitation</hi> or <hi>restri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> to any number of dayes, moneths, or years, how long they have been dead: The dead ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of God and live. Again the poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the converſion of an old man ſeems to be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or ſuppoſed, by our Saviour, in his conference with <hi>Nicodemus, Joh:</hi> 3.4, 5, 6, 7. where our Saviour denyes not the Regeneration of an old man, but taxeth <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> his groſſe ignorance, in thinking an old man, if he be borne againe, muſt needs enter into his mothers Wombe, when he is old.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Although the converſion of an old ſinner is not abſolutely <hi>impoſſible,</hi> yet 'tis a <hi>hard work;</hi> 'tis a rare and marvellous work: If a Bone be many years out of joynt, it is exceeding difficult to ſet again, now ſinners are Members out of joynt, as is intimated <hi>Galath:</hi> 6.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſet ſuch an one in joynt again. When our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt raiſed <hi>Lazarus, Joh:</hi> 11. we find that it coſt him more then to raiſe <hi>Jairus</hi> Daughter newly dead, or the Widdow of <hi>Naims</hi> ſon carried forth towards bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, he wept, he groaned in ſpirit, he prayed, he called upon <hi>Lazarus</hi> with a loud voyce, <hi>Lazarus come forth,</hi> and he troubled himſelf, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to teach us how hard a matter it is to raiſe an old ſinner from the death of ſinne to the life of grace. I have read that about three hundred and ſixty years after Chriſt, there was an old man, who had been a Pagan all his dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who in his old age hearkened after Chriſt, and ſaid he would be a Chriſtian. <hi>Simplicianus</hi> hearing him ſay ſo, would not believe him; but when the Church ſaw him a Chriſtian indeed, there was ſhouting for glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſinging in every Church, <hi>Caius Marius Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorinus is become a Christian!</hi> An old ſinner to become a young Saint is a great wonder. But yet becauſe the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94527:15"/> Converſion and Salvation of old ſinners is not impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, let me perſwade and direct the oldeſt ſinners of all, that hear me this day, to turn their feet into the way of righteouſneſſe, to accept of Salvation <hi>inter pontem &amp; fontem,</hi> (betwixt the bridge and the water, as we ſay,) to accept of a pardon when thay are juſt turning off the ladder; to accept of life now they are at the point of death; hear all ye old men and your ſouls ſhall live: Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is able and willing and ready to ſave old ſinners; if you will accept of him for your Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our upon his own (that is upon very honourable) termes.</p>
            <p>Beloved, there is yet hope concerning your ſoules: God is willing to pluck you yet as fire-brands out of the burning; to reſcue you out of the mouth of the Lyon, the roaring lyon; to ſave you out of the belly of hell, that is, out of the belly of that great <hi>Leviathan,</hi> who in his thoughts hath already ſwallowed you up. Oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, now God calls to you, ſaying, <hi>How long! How long! When will it once be? Return, return, why will you dye?</hi> Let every ſoul of you Eccho back again, ſurely <hi>this is a faithfull ſaying &amp; worthy of all acceptation, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners of which</hi> I am <hi>Chiefe,</hi> and again, <hi>How ſhall I eſcape, If I neglect ſuch great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</hi> God forbid but that this goodneſſe of God ſhould lead me to repentance. Thus reaſon or commune with thy own ſoul, before it be too late. Loe I have given the devill (God's and my ſoul's enemie) the moſt generous refined wine, my young and ſprightly dayes; and will God now accept, can God find in his heart to accept of dregs? of my old age? The devill has had the the fineſt flower, and will God be contented with the bran? the devill and my ſins have had a full harveſt, and will God to whom firſt fruits and all is due, be ſatisfied
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94527:16"/> with gleanings the devill has had the firſt-lings the beſt and fatteſt of the flock, and will God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the halt, the lame and the blind in ſacrifice? Oh the height, and depth, and bredth of the mercy of God! Oh my ſoul, my ſoul thou Shulamite, return, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. I beſeech thee by <hi>theſe mercies of God, that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth thou give up thy ſelf a holy and living ſacrifice unto God,</hi> which is but <hi>reaſonable ſervice,</hi> that <hi>thou redeem the time;</hi> and doe much for God in a little time: And now oh that my age might he renewed like the Eagles, that God would add unto my dayes many years! that the Sunne of my life might ſtand ſtill, and not haſt to goe down for many years! till I might be avenged on my luſts, the Enimies of my God, and of my ſoul! till I that have done God a great deale of diſſervice and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, might doe him a great deale of ſervice and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour! Till I have been as Eminent for holyneſſe, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I have been notorious for Prophaneſſe! And now, oh all ye that paſſe by, tell me, tell me, what ſuch an old ſinner as I ſhould doe to be ſaved?</p>
            <p>To this queſtion I anſwer, that old men muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the ſame way that young men are ſaved, and that is, by beleeving on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Lord our righteouſneſſe. Whoſoever beleeves on the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, although he be never ſo old a ſinner, ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be ſaved, ſhall in no wiſe periſh but have everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life. Doeſt thou ſee thy ſelf loſt in old <hi>Adam?</hi> doeſt ſee thy ſelf, as thou art growing up out of that old ſtock, out of that root of bitterneſſe, fit fewell for Hell-fire? doeſt ſee a neceſſity of being born again now thou art old, or elſe thou muſt dye eternally? Art weary of the body of ſinne and death, that old man of originall ſinne which thou carrieſt about with thee? Wouldeſt with all thy heart have this old man with his deeds
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94527:16"/> crucified together with Chriſt? doth it repent thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thy heart that thou haſt lived ſo long to ſo little purpoſe? that thou art ready to goe out of the world before thou haſt done almoſt any thing of the work for which thou cameſt hither? Can'ſt find in thy heart to come to Chriſt for ſalvation, from the hell that is in ſin, as well as from the hell that ſin deſerves, before thou goeſt out of the world? Dareſt venture thy ſoule upon this crucified Jeſus, and know it is no venture? Is there none in heaven or earth, no other Saviour, none that thy ſoul deſires in compariſon of him? Art reſolved in the ſtrength of Chriſt, to live in him whil'ſt thou liveſt, and to dye in Chriſt, or for Chriſt when thou dyeſt? Doeſt deſire in the matter of Juſtification, to be found not having on thy own righteouſneſſe, but the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt, and thereby to appear righteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; and for the glory of God, and to the Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy Faith before men, doeſt reſolve to endeavour that thy hoary head may be found in the way of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe? If theſe things and ſuch holy motions, reſolutions and qualifications as theſe be in thee and abound; Bleſſed art thou that ever thou wa'ſt borne; thou ſhalt not dye, but live; this day I aſſure thee ſalvation is come unto thy ſoul: Jeſus Chriſt hath given thee life, a new life in thy old age. Men it may be, think it almoſt impoſſible, that a valley of dry bones ſhould live; and ſay as 'tis <hi>Ezek:</hi> 37. <hi>can theſe dry bones live?</hi> who would ever have ſaid, that ſuch an old ſinner ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have proved a young convert? But God that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the dead, he ſaith to his Prophets, <hi>Propheſie upon theſe bones, and ſay unto them, oh ye dry bones, hear the word of the Lord;</hi> and who knows but that ſome of theſe dry bones may live? Truely my prayer for theſe old men ſhall be, to the God of my life and theirs, that they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94527:17"/> might all live in his ſight, that they might all live for ever: And for you all that hear me this day, oh that God would bind up all your ſouls in the bundle of life! oh that ye might have part in the firſt reſurrection, that on you the ſecond death might have no power! oh that ye might be changed from nature to grace, before your change by death come, that your change may be for the better, and not for the worſe! But leaſt any from the poſſibility of the ſalvation of the oldeſt and chiefeſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners take heart to put off their repentance to old age, leaſt any ſuck poyſon from ſo ſweet a flower, take by way of Caution or Antidote theſe two or three Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That old ſinners, who have all their time enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the means of grace, have rarely been known to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and repent in their age, when there is but a ſtep betwixt them and death, &amp; ſo betwixt them and hell.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That thoſe labourers in the Parable who came into the vineyard to work at the eleventh hour, were not cald untill the eleventh hour. <hi>Math:</hi> 20. The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was put by an old Indian Sagamore, or gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in New England, to one of the Engliſh Miniſters; Whether our God and Saviour would receive an old ſinner, ſuch as he was? The Miniſter anſwered, doubtleſſe he would, conſidering this old man had never heard of Chriſt 'til his old age, and came in when called.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That there was a time, when wiſedome ſtop'd her eares at their crie, who refufed to hear when ſhe called. <hi>Prov:</hi> 1.24. Let not young ſinners goe on in their ſins, thinking to return when they are old, for that is the way never to live to be old, or if they doe, they rarely repent in age. Yet let not old ſinners deſpaire, whoever comes unto Chriſt, he will in no wiſe caſt out.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94527:17"/> And as for you old men, whoſe hoarie heads are found in the way of righteouſneſſe, Goe on and proſper, and the Lord be with you; Be, as <hi>Noah</hi> was, Preachers of righteouſneſſe in your generation; See that ye ſhine as lights in the midſt of a crooked generation. Be exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of holineſſe to younger ones; call upon them: to remember their Creatour betimes, in the dayes of their youth; teach them the way they ſhould goe, that they may not forſake it when they are old. And eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ye who are fathers and mothers, let the ſoules of your children be precious in your eyes: doe not offer your ſons and daughters unto devills, and bring them forth and up to the great <hi>Abaddon,</hi> or murtherer of <hi>ſoules</hi> for want of religious education, Be earneſt with God, night and day with teares and Prayers, and with your children by inſtruction, reprehenſion, correction, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that ſo your children may riſe up and call you bleſſed, may bleſſe God for you, and with you. Oh what a joy and rejoycing, ye pious fathers and mothers, will it be to you, to meet Jeſus Chriſt at the great day with ſuch like words as he uſed to his father, Loe here are we and the children thou haſt given us; of all thou haſt given us, have we loſt none; there's never a ſon or daughter of perdition amongſt <hi>them; thine they were, thou gaveſt them us, and they have kept thy word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude all, men, brethren, and fathers, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to ſuffer the word of exhortation, I ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you <hi>Young men,</hi> and exhort, ſaying, Be ye <hi>righteous,</hi> that ye may be <hi>old;</hi> this will be your <hi>crown,</hi> and the <hi>length</hi> of your dayes. I ſpeak unto you <hi>old men,</hi> and exhort ſaying, Oh be ye righteous and religious, this will be <hi>your crown,</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> better then that of a <hi>hoarie</hi> head; be <hi>holy,</hi> and ye ſhall be <hi>happy;</hi> live <hi>well,</hi> and live for <hi>ever.</hi> And ye that have been young, and religious, and old &amp;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94527:18"/> religious too, young Saints &amp; old Saints, Oh be not wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, faint not, hold out, ye are not far from the kingdome of heaven, you are near the Goal, your labour and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile is almoſt at an end, you ſhall have crown for crown, for this <hi>corruptible crown of glory of old age,</hi> you ſhall have a crown of glory, which is reſerved in heaven for you, which is <hi>incorruptible:</hi> your old bodyes ſhall be new caſt in the <hi>grave,</hi> as in a new <hi>mould,</hi> and all the <hi>wrinkles, cracks,</hi> and <hi>flawes,</hi> ſhall be mended: and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you have now a crown of glory upon your <hi>head</hi> in your old age, you ſhall then have a <hi>body</hi> all glorified, and all glorious, you ſhall be made like unto the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous body of Chriſt, that is, you ſhall ſhine as the Sunne in the kingdome of your Father. Inſtead of <hi>long</hi> life on <hi>earth,</hi> you ſhall have <hi>eternall</hi> life in <hi>heaven:</hi> You ſhall ſit down with the holy Patriarcks, <hi>Abraham, Iſaack,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in the kingdom of heaven. Yea thus bleſſed and glorious ſhall ye all be, both young and old, who are found, living and dying, in the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
